<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Why the name ?</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Vincent Massol" email="vmassol@users.sourceforge.net"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>

    <s1 title="Why Cactus ?">

      <p>
        Here are some stories and reasons about the 'Cactus' name :)
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          It's a cool name ... Short, easy to pronounce, same meanings in all
          spoken languages, has some punch ...
        </li>
        <li>
          There is a cool french song by Jacques Dutronc about cacti that
          goes "le monde entier est un cactus ..." (the whole world is a
          Cactus). The lyrics is available
          <link href="http://miditext.com/Textes/24859.htm">here</link> and
          the music (.wma format)
          <link href="http://miditext.com/wma/24859.wma">here</link>. It is a
          song that says that cacti are everywhere and that everything is
          a cactus. I like that ! :) ...
        </li>
        <li>
          The J2EEUnit name (which was the previous name of Cactus) was fine
          but there was a Sun trademark on the J2EE part of the name ...
        </li>
        <li>
          Cactus is actually an acronym ... ha ha .. for Computer Assisted
          Construction of Test Unit for the Server, or Cool and Comprehensive
          Test Unit for the Server, or ... (please send your suggestions to
          the <link href="mailinglist.html">Cactus mailing list</link>).
        </li>
        <li>
          The company for which I work (
          <link href="http://www.octo.com">OCTO Technology</link>) had
          organized a diner to celebrate our 3
          years of existence. I was looking for a new name for J2EEUnit. I
          asked some workmates to help me look for a name. We tried to
          find a name which had something to do with the Apache name. We thought
          of indians of course ... we tried several names and then Dominique
          said "Cactus" (you know, indians, the desert, cacti. That's one
          clich&eacute; of indians we have here in France !). I immediatly liked
          it ...
        </li>
        <li>
          The Cactus name has a rich visual iconography associated with it. So
          it should be possible to find a nice and funny logo (I'm still
          looking for the perfect logo ... If you have proposition, you can
          send them to the <link href="mailinglist.html">Cactus mailing list
          </link> (there is currently a <link href="logos.html">logo contest
          </link> going on ! Try defeating the current logo if you think you
          have better !).
        </li>
        <li>
          A Cactus is full of spines. Visually you can imagine that a piece of
          code that has gone through this rigourous and comprehensive testing
          has had all it's bug revealed ! ...
        </li>
        <li>
          We can imagine a motto like "Tested on Apache-Cactus" !
        </li>
        <li>
          Any more ... ?
        </li>
      </ul>

    </s1>

  </body>
</document>