<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE changes SYSTEM "./dtd/changes-v10.dtd">

<changes title="History of Changes">

  <devs>
    <person name="Vincent Massol" email="vmassol@users.sourceforge.net" id="VMA"/>
  </devs>

  <release version="1.0b2 in CVS" date="">
    <action dev="VMA" type="add">
      Added a
      <link href="scope.html">"Cactus scope and status"</link> page on the web
      site that explains the current scope and status of Cactus.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="add">
      Added a
      <link href="goals.html">"Cactus goals"</link> page on the web site that
      gives rough goals and guidelines for the future of Cactus.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update" due-to="Jeff Turner" due-to-email="jeff@socialchange.net.au">
      Improved build process so that it nows works even if junit, stylebook, ..
      jars are not in the <code>CLASSPATH</code> prior to running the build.
    </action>
  </release>

  <release version="1.0b1" date="April 9 2001">
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Updated the Cactus distribution so that everything is contained into one
      single file (doc + jars + sample). The sources are available separately
      in a second file.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="add">
      Added a section on the main web site page to explain the reason for the
      Cactus name.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Tested with JUnit 3.6.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Changed the web site skin to be the Jakarta skin and not the Apache XML
      skin. This is because Cactus is now part of the Jakarta Commons project.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Updated the web site installation section to better explain the
      required steps to install Cactus. Namely, it covers
      <link href="installation_ant.html">installing Ant</link> and
      <link href="installation_sample.html">installing the Cactus Sample
      application</link>.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="remove">
      Removed the deliverable dependencies jar. Instead, provides a zipped
      installation of Ant containing the needed jars for tasks used by Cactus
      and Cactus Sample build files.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Removed the <code>misc/</code> directory and JBuilder files from CVS
      and source distribution.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Renamed the project from J2EEUnit to Cactus. Although it was a difficult
      decision to make, it had to be done as J2EE is a Sun trademark. Renamed
      all occurrences of J2EEUnit to Cactus and changed package names (from
      <code>j2eeunit.*</code> to <code>org.apache.commons.castor.*</code>.
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="fix">
      The sample application sources now contains all needed configuration
      files (the manifest and web.xml files were missing in the previous
      release).
    </action>
    <action dev="VMA" type="update">
      Donated the project to the Apache Software Foundation.
      Changed license from GPL to APL. Moved packages from
      <code>j2eeunit.*</code> to <code>org.apache.commons.j2eeunit.*</code>
      and changed copyrights
    </action>
  </release>

</changes>