<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Cactus</title>
    <subtitle>Server-Side Unit Testing Framework</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="Vincent Massol" email="vmassol@users.sourceforge.net"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>

    <s1 title="Project description">
      <p>
        Cactus is a simple test framework for unit testing server-side java
        code. It is based on <link href="http://junit.org">JUnit</link>.
        It's primary goal is to be able to unit test server side java methods
        which use Servlet objects such as <code>HttpServletRequest</code>,
        <code>HttpServletResponse</code>, <code>HttpSession</code>, ... (see
        the full <link href="features.html">feature list</link>). This
        framework is <em>not</em> a functional test framework which views your
        server classes as a black box and only tests the returned results
        from externally calling your application (see
        <link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/httpunit">HttpUnit</link>
        for this). Both frameworks are complementary.
      </p>
    </s1>

    <s1 title="Latest news">
      <table>
        <tr>
          <td>
            09/04/2001
          </td>
          <td>
            Cactus 1.0 beta 1 is available for
            <link href="downloads.html">download</link>. Check the updated
            <link href="features.html">feature list</link> and the
            <link href="changes.html">changes</link> for the details.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            09/04/2001
          </td>
          <td>
            The web site has been updated to reflect the modifications that
            occurred during the donation to Apache and the change of name :
            the license has changed to APL, the packages have moved from
            <code>j2eeunit.*</code> to <code>org.apache.commons.cactus.*</code>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            09/04/2001
          </td>
          <td>
            J2EEUnit has been renamed to Cactus.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            09/04/2001
          </td>
          <td>
            J2EEUnit has been donated to the Apache Software Foundation.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      
    </s1>

    <s1 title="Why the name ?">

      <p>
        Here are some stories and reasons about the name :)
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          It's a cool name ... Short, easy to pronounce, same meanings in all
          spoken languages, has some punch ...
        </li>
        <li>
          There is a cool french song by Jacques Dutronc about Cactuses that
          goes "le monde entier est un cactus ..." (the whole world is a
          Cactus). The lyrics is available
          <link href="http://miditext.com/Textes/24859.htm">here</link> and
          the music (.wma format)
          <link href="http://miditext.com/wma/24859.wma">here</link>. It is a
          song that says that cactuses are everywhere and that everything is
          a cactus. I like that ! :) ...
        </li>
        <li>
          The J2EEUnit name (which was the previous name of Cactus) was fine
          but there was a Sun trademark on the J2EE part of the name ...
        </li>
        <li>
          Cactus is actually an acronym ... ha ha .. for Computer Assisted
          Construction of Test Unit for the Server, or Cool and Comprehensive
          Test Unit for the Server, or ... (please send your suggestions to
          <link href="mailto:vmassol@users.sourceforge.net">me</link>) ...
        </li>
        <li>
          The company for which I work (<link href="http://www.octo.com">
          OCTO Technology</link>) had organized a diner to celebrate our 3
          years of existence. I was looking for a new name for J2EEUnit. I
          asked some workmates of mine to help me look for a name. We tried to
          find a name which had something to do with the Apache name. We though
          of indians of course ... we tried several names and then Dominique
          said "Cactus" (you know, indians, the desert, cactuses. That's one
          clich&eacute; of indians we have here in France !). I immediatly liked
          it ...
        </li>
        <li>
          The Cactus name has a rich visual iconography associated with it. So
          it should be possible to find a nice and funny logo (I'm still
          looking for the perfect logo ... Again if you have ideas, you can
          send them to 
          <link href="mailto:vmassol@users.sourceforge.net">me</link>) ...
        </li>
        <li>
          A Cactus is full of spines. Visually you can imagine that a piece of
          code that has gone through this rigourous and comprehensive testing
          has had all it's bug revealed ! ...
        </li>
        <li>
          We can imagine a motto like "Tested on Apache-Cactus" !
        </li>
        <li>
          Any more ... ?
        </li>
      </ul>

    </s1>

  </body>
</document>