<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE todo SYSTEM "./dtd/todo-v10.dtd">

<todo title="Things To Do for Cactus">

  <devs>
    <person name="Vincent Massol" email="vmassol@users.sourceforge.net" id="VMA"/>
    <person name="P. Babu Naidu" email="pbnaidu99@hotmail.com" id="BNA"/>
  </devs>

  <actions priority="medium">
    <action context="docs">
      Write a tutorial that shows how to test EJBs.
    </action>
    <action context="samples">
      Add a sample that shows how to test EJBs.
    </action>
    <action context="design">
      Add support for testing custom JSP Taglibs (suggested by Sohail Aslam) +
      tutorial + sample
    </action>
    <action context="design" assigned-to="VMA">
      Add support for testing Servlet API 2.3 Filters.
    </action>
    <action context="design" assigned-to="BNA">
      Provide support for easier testing of EJBs by writing an EJB Redirector
      (which is a EJB Session Bean) so that it is possible to test EJB methods
      that uses EJB container API like security checks, transaction, JNDI
      calls, ... (requested by notyy).
    </action>
  </actions>

  <actions priority="low">
    <action context="docs">
      Write a Cactus integration tutorial for JBuilder 4.
    </action>
    <action context="docs">
      Write a Cactus integration tutorial for VAJava 3.5.
    </action>
    <action context="build">
      Add Ant scripts to support WebLogic 6.0.
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Handle <code>getRealPath()</code>, <code>getPathTranslated()</code> in the
      <code>ServletRedirectorRequest</code> class.
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Add API in <code>ServletTestRequest</code> to send data to the URL
      connection output stream. This is to easily test code that sends bytes
      of data as POST data to the servlet (requested by Daniel Cohen and 
      custommonkey).
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Automatically add the query string parameters defined when using the
      <code>ServletTestRequest.setURL()</code> API to the list of parameters
      passed to the server redirector, so that it won't be necessary to call
      <code>ServletTestRequest.addParameter()</code> for each of these
      parameters.
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Check why zipped distributable files have a mode of 644 on unix systems
      (it should rather be 755). Thanks to Jason Crickmer.
    </action>
    <action context="docs">
      Add a FAQ entry for explaining unit testing of persistent sessions.
    </action>
  </actions>

  <actions priority="wish">
    <action context="code">
      Create a Cactus Doclet. This will introduce new javadoc tags (like the
      <link href="">EJBDoclet</link>) that will be used by the javadoc command
      to do several things : generate test classes and test methods, generate
      richer documentation. Indeed, the best documentation for a method is
      it's test methods that show how to use it effectively. So maybe we could
      append to the HTML javadoc for a method the java test method code as an
      example.
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Integration for Netbeans by integration with the Netbeans XTest module.
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Look at <link href="http://jxunit.sourceforge.net">JXUnit</link> to
      see if an integration with Cactus can be done (proposed by Will Sargent).
    </action>
  </actions>

</todo>