<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE todo SYSTEM "./dtd/todo-v10.dtd">

<todo title="Things To Do for Cactus">

  <devs>
    <person name="Vincent Massol" email="vmassol@users.sourceforge.net" id="VMA"/>
    <person name="P. Babu Naidu" email="pbn@bea.com" id="BNA"/>
  </devs>

  <actions priority="medium">
    <action context="docs">
      Write a tutorial that shows how to test EJBs.
    </action>
    <action context="samples">
      Add a sample that shows how to test EJBs.
    </action>
    <action context="design" assigned-to="VMA">
      Add support for testing custom JSP Taglibs (suggested by Sohail Aslam) +
      tutorial + sample
    </action>
    <action context="design" assigned-to="VMA">
      Add support for testing Servlet API 2.3 Filters.
    </action>
    <action context="design" assigned-to="BNA">
      Provide a mechanism for easier testing of EJBs. The mechanism is to be
      defined (requested by notyy).
    </action>
  </actions>

  <actions priority="low">
    <action context="code">
      Make the methods <code>setUp()</code> and <code>tearDown()</code>
      protected on the server side so that it is consistent with JUnit (for the
      moment they need to be public to work).
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Manage multivalued HTTP headers in <code>ServletTestRequest</code>.
    </action>
    <action context="docs">
      Write a Cactus integration tutorial for JBuilder 4.
    </action>
    <action context="docs">
      Write a Cactus integration tutorial for VAJava 3.5.
    </action>
    <action context="build">
      Add Ant scripts to support WebLogic 6.0.
    </action>
    <action context="code" assigned-to="VMA">
      Handle <code>getRealPath()</code>, <code>getPathTranslated()</code> in the
      <code>ServletRedirectorRequest</code> class.
    </action>
    <action context="admin" assigned-to="VMA">
      On the Cactus news web page, provide a list of pages that have been
      recently modified so that end users can see at a glance what has changed
      recently on the web site.
    </action>
    <action context="build" assigned-to="VMA">
      Generate changelog file from CVS change log information and put in the
      documentation of each release.
    </action>
    <action context="docs" assigned-to="VMA">
      Add a license section to the Cactus web site that explains that Cactus
      is under the APL license and shows the license statement.
    </action>
    <action context="docs" assigned-to="VMA">
      Add a contributing section to the Cactus web site (see the contributing
      section of Cocoon as a sample).
    </action>
    <action context="build" assigned-to="VMA">
      On the documentation web pages (i.e. not the site web pages) add a sub
      header for each page with a message saying "Click here if you want to
      see the latest online version of this page". Modify a stylebook stylesheet
      to do this (combined with an Ant token filter or an Ant replace task).
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Add API in <code>ServletTestRequest</code> to send data to the URL
      connection output stream. This is to easily test code that sends bytes
      of data as POST data to the servlet (requested by Daniel Cohen and 
      custommonkey).
    </action>
    <action context="code">
      Automatically add the query string parameters defined when using the
      <code>ServletTestRequest.setURL()</code> API to the list of parameters
      passed to the server redirector, so that it won't be necessary to call
      <code>ServletTestRequest.addParameter()</code> for each of these
      parameters.
    </action>
  </actions>

  <actions priority="wish">
    <action context="code">
      Integration for Netbeans by integration with the Netbeans XTest module.
    </action>
  </actions>

</todo>