<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
 * ========================================================================
 * 
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 * contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 * this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 * The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 * (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 * the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 * 
 *   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 * 
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 * 
 * ========================================================================
-->

<document id="goals"
          xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>Cactus goals</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="General goals">

            <ul>
                <li>
                    Provide a simple unit testing framework focused on server side java
                    code which tries to cover all J2EE component models and potentially
                    other type of components.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Allow fine-grained continuous testing of all files making up
                    an application: source code but also meta-data files (such as
                    deployment descriptors, etc) through an in-container approach.
                    Integration work is costly and Cactus tries to spread this load
                    by doing it during development in an automated way.
                </li>
            </ul>

        </section>

        <section name="Medium terms goals and ideas">

            <p>
                The short term goals for Cactus are to continue providing and improving
                support for J2EE unit testing. More specifically the following areas
                are being considered and researched:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>
                    Integrate Cactus with JUnit4, which will allow
                    to write annotation-based test-cases,
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add support for testing Java Portlets and/or Web-services
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add support for Servlet API 2.5/JSP 2.2 (by using
                    Tomcat 5/Resin 3.x),
                </li>
                <li>
                    Provide a full servlet container test suite a la Watchdog using Cactus.,
                </li>
                <li>
                    Performance unit testing: Add performance extensions to be able to
                    test each single method in performance.
                </li>
                <li>
                    More tutorial on AspectJ testing. Potentially add a Cactus Aspect
                    extension to allow writing test cases as Aspects (this may allow to
                    remove the need for Cactus redirectors).
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add EJB Redirectors to be able to unit test Session Beans, Entity
                    Beans and MessageDriven Beans
                </li>
                <li>
                    Decouple the Cactus framework into the core and its "plugins". This
                    means to publish a public API and a public SPI. The SPI would allow
                    to support plugin for testing different type of components (Servlet,
                    Entity EJB, Struts Actions, etc).
                </li>
            </ul>

        </section>

        <section name="Long term vision">

            <subsection name="The Future of Component Unit Testing">

                <p>
                    We believe unit testing server side components is going to get harder
                    and harder in the future, unless something is done about it!
                    Even now, depending on the specifications
                    for a given component model it is more or less easy. Sometimes it is
                    even not feasible to test all kind of code.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We believe that we will see more and more components in the future.
                    By components we mean pieces of code that execute in a container.
                    The container will provide more and more services for the components
                    (like transactions, security, life cycle, persistence, interfaces
                    - like web services -, logging, ...). The consequences will be:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        testing strategies that are not in-container, like Mock Objects
                        will still very useful but will provide less added value in
                        ensuring that the code behaves ok. Indeed, as the components will
                        rely more and more on the container's services, the confidence that
                        the tests will run well when deployed will decrease and the need
                        for a solution that ensures the code will run correctly in its
                        environment will increase,
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        it will become more and more difficult to offer an in-container
                        unit testing framework that lives outside the container.
                    </li>
                </ul>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Long term goals for Cactus">

                <p>
                    Consequently to the above predictions, there are 2 long term goals
                    for Cactus:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Continue with the in-container approach as much as possible. It is
                        a best try effort in order to provide tests in which you can have
                        a good confidence,
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        However, we believe the only satisfactory and long term solution
                        is to include (unit) testing APIs as <em>part</em> of the container
                        specifications. This could be done in the form of a SPI
                        (Service Provider Interface) against which a generic unit testing
                        framework could be plugged, thus leaving the implementation details
                        to an external framework and only providing maybe a generic
                        and simple implementation. Thus, one goal of Cactus is to help
                        specify needed container API/SPI for unit testing,
                        i.e. create
                        an additional service of the container: a "unit-testing service"
                        (in addition to the existing Security, Transaction, Life Cycle, ...
                        Services). The ultimate
                        goal will be reached when this new API/SPI is accepted and become
                        a de jure standard. It would then be time to think about
                        integrating it into the Servlet Specifications
                        (or other components -like EJBs -
                        specifications). Agreed, this far-streched at the current time
                        but it is the Cactus vision!
                    </li>
                </ul>

            </subsection>

        </section>

        <section name="Feedback needed!">

            <p>
                Cactus is an open source project where everyone is free to participate
                (and even encouraged). Thus, we'd really like to have your opinions on
                the subject of Cactus future.
            </p>
            <p>
                How do you view the future of Cactus?
            </p>
            <p>
                Do you like the goals and vision defined above?
            </p>
            <p>
                Please send all answers to the
                <a href="mail-lists.html">Cactus mailing list</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Thanks.
            </p>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
