<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
 * ========================================================================
 * 
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 * contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 * this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 * The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 * (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 * the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 * 
 *   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 * 
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 * 
 * ========================================================================
-->

<document id="mock_vs_cactus"
          xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>Mock Objects vs In-Container testing</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Mock Objects vs In-Container testing">
            <blockquote class="warn warningmark">
                <strong>
                    This article was written about 2 years ago and is starting to
                    be a bit old. The general content is still valid but several
                    details are no longer true as the frameworks (be it Cactus or
                    the mock objects frameworks) have evolved since then.
                </strong>
            </blockquote>
            <blockquote class="info infomark">
                Throughout this article, we'll use the abbreviations MO for Mock
                Objects and IC for In-Container strategy.
            </blockquote>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <a href="mock_vs_cactus.html#mo_serverside">MO and Server-side tests</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="mock_vs_cactus.html#mo_example">An example</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="mock_vs_cactus.html#mo_differences">Differences between MO and IC</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="mock_vs_cactus.html#mo_conclusion">Conclusion</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="mock_vs_cactus.html#mo_resources">MO resources</a>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="MO and Server-side tests" id="mo_serverside">

            <p>
                MO is a strategy to unit test java classes in general. As such
                it is also applicable to unit test server side code like Servlets,
                Filters, Taglibs, EJBs, ... See the original article
                <a href="http://mockobjects.sourceforge.net/endotesting.html">
                    "Endo-Testing: Unit Testing with Mock Objects"
                </a>
                for full details
                on MO. As such it is a challenger to Cactus but we'll see
                in the rest of this article that it is in fact complementary rather than
                a replacement.
            </p>
            <p>
                The main goal of MO is to unit test a method in isolation of other
                domain objects. Thus, the MO approach is to fake domain objects
                by using simulated copies instead of the real objects (be careful
                MO does not implement any logic in its fake objects, that would be
                "stubbing". All behaviours of mock objects are controlled by the unit
                test itself). This enables to
                finely unit test the method with no environment
                "noise" and to concentrate on unit testing its logic.
            </p>
            <p>
                When applied to servlet testing, it means mock objects need
                to be provided for simulating the servlet container. In other words
                a mock implementation of the Servlet API need to be provided (of course
                only the Servlet API methods used in the classes under test need to be
                mocked and the approach described in the white paper is to start small
                and develop the mock implementations as they are needed - Note that
                mock objects can even be generated at build time or at run time with
                JDK 1.3 dynamic proxies, see
                <a href="mock_vs_cactus.html#mo_resources">resources</a>-).
            </p>
            <p>
                Cactus' strategy on the other hand has been to rely on the real
                container to provide the implementation of the Servlet API.
                In the rest of this article, we'll discuss the pros and cons of each
                approach and draw a conclusion.
            </p>
            <p>
                Let's start first by an example to understand better what are MO.
            </p>

        </section>

        <section name="An example" id="mo_example">

            <p>
                Simple test case using Cactus:
            </p>

            <source><![CDATA[
[...]
    MyServlet myServlet = new MyServlet();
[...]

public void beginXXX(WebRequest theRequest)
{
    theRequest.addParameter("param1", "value1");
    theRequest.addParameter("param2", "value2");
}

public void testXXX()
{
    myServlet.init(config);

    myServlet.myMethod(request, response);
    assertEquals("some value", session.getAttribute("some_name_set_in_mymethod"));
}

public void endXXX(WebResponse theResponse)
{
    String result = theResponse.getText();
    assertEquals("<html><head/><body>A GET request</body></html>", result);
}

]]></source>

            <p>
                Simple test case using Mock Objects:
            </p>

            <source><![CDATA[
[...]
    MockHttpServletRequest myMockHttpRequest = new MockHttpServletRequest();
    MockHttpServletResponse myMockHttpResponse = new MockHttpServletResponse();
    MockServletConfig myMockServletConfig = new MockServletConfig();
    MyServlet myServlet = new MyServlet();
[...]

public void testXXX()
{
    myMockHttpRequest.setupAddParameter("param1", "value1");
    myMockHttpRequest.setupAddParameter("param2", "value2");

    myMockHttpRequest.setExpectedAttribute("some_name_set_in_mymethod", "some value");
    myMockHttpResponse.setExpectedOutput("<html><head/><body>A GET request</body></html>");

    myServlet.init(myMockServletConfig);
    myServlet.myMethod(myMockHttpRequest, myMockHttpResponse);

    myMockHttpRequest.verify();
    myMockHttpResponse.verify();
}
]]></source>

        </section>

        <section name="Differences between MO and IC" id="mo_differences">

            <p>
                Comparison of pros and cons of MO versus IC.
            </p>
            <blockquote class="info infomark">
                This table is not meant to be comprehensive in
                term of benefits/inconvenients of using MO. It is more focused on
                pros and cons of MO when used for unit testing server side code (i.e.
                what Cactus is focusing on).
            </blockquote>
            <blockquote class="info infomark">
                A '+' indicates a positive point.For example
                a '+' in the MO column shows that it has an advantage over IC.
            </blockquote>

            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>
                        Issues
                    </th>
                    <th>
                        MO
                    </th>
                    <th>
                        IC
                    </th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        MO let us test methods even before the domain objects are ready,
                        i.e. before the implementation are ready. Or before a choice of
                        implementation has been made. Thus, for example, it is possible to
                        write servlet code before choosing a container. This is in
                        accordance with XP that says: "not commit to infrastructure choice
                        before you have to" and "write unit test first".
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        MO is comprehensive/universal. It adapts to all kind of unit
                        testing:
                        Servlet unit testing, JDBC unit testing, Struts unit testing, ...
                        Cactus only addresses server-side testing, meaning that if in your
                        Servlet code you have JDBC connections and you want to unit test
                        in isolation the methods that does database access you still need
                        to have a MO-like strategy, thus you need to understand and learn 2
                        strategies.
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        Running MO tests is very fast as it does not rely on having to run
                        a container. Thus tests can be run very often. IC testing needs to
                        start the container, run the tests, stop the container. However,
                        this can be alleviated by using Ant and by using a reloadable
                        container (the majority of containers implement dynamic reloading).
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        Using MO force the developer to refactor his code. As an example he
                        needs to ensure that interfaces are provided for domain objects so
                        that a Mock implementation can be implemented. There are other
                        more subtle refactoring involved like smart handler passing instead
                        of more fine grained data (thus leading to better encapsulation). It
                        follows XP refactoring rules. Note that if you need to implement
                        tests for existing code it can easily become a nightmare ...
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        Using MO, it is not sure the classes will run correctly in the
                        chosen container. On the other hand, IC tests ensures that
                        all code will run perfectly well in container.
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        MO tests tend to be very fine-grained. Thus, there is no assurance
                        that object interactions will work properly and thus more coarse
                        grained tests tests are a must (integration tests, functional
                        tests).
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        Using generic MO libraries is against some of MO practices. For
                        example, a good practice is to factorize domain object asserts in
                        the mock implementation instead of in the test case (this is called
                        Refactored Assertions). This is
                        possible only if the Mock implementation is project specific. So,
                        for some parts, MO does not fit that well with the idea of generic
                        libraries. A middle ground could probably be found.
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        Using MO is not simple. It needs some discipline and some
                        experience. Same as for unit tesing using JUnit, there are some
                        methodologies to follow. Some are:
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                In order not to be weighted down by having to implement myriad
                                of MO, these implementation need to be the simplest possible,
                                i.e. do nothing method at first and then slowly over time,
                                during refactoring, implement what is needed at the current
                                time.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                One must resist the temptation to reimplement the domain logic
                                in the MO. There must be almost no logic at all in MO.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                MO must not make calls to other MOs ... When it happens, there
                                is a need for MO refactoring !
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        In some cases MO mandates creating API that are no normally
                        needed, like having to offer a
                        <code>init(MockObject)</code>
                        method in a Servlet in order to
                        initialize a mock version of an internally used domain object. Also
                        the code may become more complex (even if more flexible) because
                        of the need for testing and not because of business requirements:
                        for example, one might need to introduce a factory when it was not
                        needed simply to be able to provide MO objects from the factory.
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        It may not be possible to create generic MO libraries that fit all
                        the needs. For example a generic JDBC MO library may not be possible
                        and might need database specific MO libraries. Also the cost and
                        complexity of a generic MO library may be higher than just
                        reimplementing from scratch just the needed mocked parts.
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        MO does not always work well. For example the API being mocked need
                        to offer the correct interfaces and means to override/set internal
                        objects.
                    </td>
                    <td/>
                    <td>
                        +
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>

        </section>

        <section name="Conclusion" id="mo_conclusion">

            <p>
                Mock Objects are a very interesting way of doing unit testing which
                could bridge the gap between standard java class unit testing and
                server-side testing of container components. The biggest
                difference between the way Cactus currently works and Mock Objects is
                that Cactus tests tend to be more coarse-grained and they also ensure
                that developed code will run in the container. On the other hand, Mock
                Objects are more satisfactory intellectually because they are not
                limited to servlet unit testing but cover the whole spectrum of code.
            </p>
            <p>
                We believe the graininess of Cactus tests is just correct. Having
                fine-grained tests is nice but it is also a lot of effort. It seems
                Cactus
                tests are a middle ground where you can still do unit tests fine
                enough and at the same time it gives you *enough* confidence that your
                tests will run fine when deployed.
            </p>
            <p>
                Also, as described on the <a href="goals.html">Cactus' goals
                page</a>, we think that a framework like Cactus will be more and
                more useful as we use more and more components in the future because
                it will provide
                the needed confidence that the code will run ok in the container.
            </p>
            <p>
                We also believe that writing correctly MO tests is a difficult process
                that need some training. MO are good because they let you write better
                code but it is more difficult to understand than Cactus tests.
            </p>
            <p>
                Finally, we believe that MO and Cactus are complementary in 2 areas:
            </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        During the development phase, MO could be used to unit test the
                        code logic only. They run fast and you could use them easily
                        inside your IDE. Then every few hours, you'll run the Cactus tests
                        which test interactions between objects and container interactions.
                        Then you'll run the functional/acceptance tests when you deploy
                        to the real platform. Note that this is if you want to do the full
                        cycle. A short cycle could simply be Cactus tests and functional
                        /acceptance tests.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Cactus focuses on server side code. However you can use MO (or
                        stubs) within Cactus tests for simulating a JDBC connection, an
                        LDAP connection, ... for example. There are no restrictions.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            <p>
                We would very much like to have your feedback on MO vs IC. Please post
                your feedback on the
                <a href="mail-lists.html">Cactus mailing list</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Thanks a lot.
            </p>

        </section>

        <section name="Resources on MO" id="mo_resources">

            <p>
                Some links:
            </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://www.mockobjects.com/wiki/MocksObjectsPaper?action=AttachFile&amp;do=get&amp;target=mockobjects.pdf">
                            "Endo-Testing: Unit Testing with Mock Objects"
                        </a>
                        (PDF).
                        Describes the vision behind MO.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?MockObject">Mock Object discussions on
                            Wiki</a>.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://www.mockobjects.com/">Mock Object project</a>
                        on
                        SourceForge. MO framework and some static mock implementations.
                        Also supports runtime mocks using Dynamic Proxies.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://mockmaker.sourceforge.net/">MockMaker</a>. Generates build
                        time MO implementations for the SourceForge Mock Objects project.
                        Generation is done from interfaces or classes.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://easymock.org/">Easy Mock</a>.
                        Uses Dynamic Proxies (JDK 1.3) to provide runtime
                        mock implementations, thus eliminating the need for generating/
                        writing the mock implementations.
                    </li>
                </ul>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
