<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
 * ========================================================================
 * 
 * Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
 * contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
 * this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
 * The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
 * (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
 * the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 * 
 *   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 * 
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 * 
 * ========================================================================
-->

<document id="contributors"
          xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>Contributors</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Meritocracy">

            <p>
                All work on Cactus is contributed by volunteers whose only motivation
                is to help make Cactus work even better, both for themselves and for
                rest of the community.
            </p>
            <p>
                All contributions are welcome (see the
                <a href="index.html">Participating</a>
                page).
                The final decision of what becomes part of the official distribution
                is made by a group of <a href="#committers">Committers</a>.
                For more about Meritocracy, see the
                <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/roles.html">Management page</a>
                on the Apache
                Jakarta Website.
            </p>

        </section>
        <section name="Committers">
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:vmassol@apache.org">Vincent Massol</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:jariw@hyperlink-interactive.co.uk">Jari Worsley</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:ndlesiecki@yahoo.com">Nicholas Lesiecki</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:jruaux@octo.com">Julien Ruaux</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:cmlenz@gmx.de">Christopher Lenz</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:felipeal@apache.org">Felipe Leme</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:suguri.kazuhito@lab.ntt.co.jp">Kazuhito Suguri</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:grimsell@apache.org">Magnus Grimsell</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:nchalumeau@apache.org">Nicolas Chalumeau</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:ptahchiev@apache.org">Petar Tahchiev</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="Contributors">

            <p>By alphabetical order on the last name:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:paston@bea.com">Philip Aston</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:cchabanois@ifrance.com">Cedric Chabanois</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:Bob.Davison@reuters.com">Bob Davison</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:julien@julien-dubois.com">Julien Dubois</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:andrew.forman@wcom.com">Andrew B Forman</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:jgrelier@octo.com">Jerome Grelier</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:ahasegawa@borland.com">Atsushi Hasegawa</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:Todd_Idler@jdedwards.com">Todd Idler</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:kaarle.kaila@iki.fi">Kaarle Kaila</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:digital@ix.net.au">Robert Leftwich</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:alan@digitalmonkey.co.uk">Alan Perfect</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:Jason.Robertson@acs-inc.com">Jason Robertson</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="#">Matt Sullivan</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:Kunal_Vaishnav@jdedwards.com">Kunal Vaishnav</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:hudsoncwwong@yahoo.com">Hudson Wong</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:pwong@sct.com">Peter Wong</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <a href="mailto:sean.zhang@verizon.com">Sean Zhang</a>
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>


        <section name="Special thanks">

            <p>
                Thanks to all that have reported bugs or suggested ideas for Cactus.
            </p>

            <p>
                Thanks to all that have participated to the
                <a href="logos.html">Cactus Logo</a>
                competitions and especially
                Lyonel Thouvenot who had his logo up on the Cacus web
                site from 2002 to April 2005:
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="images/logos/lthouvenot.gif" alt="Proposition 1: Classic"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                Special thanks also to Eoghan McIlwaine who has designed the current
                Cactus logo.
            </p>
            <p>
                And, of course ...
            </p>
            <p>
                Thanks to the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">Apache Jakarta</a> project
                for accepting the donation of J2EEUnit (renamed Cactus), thus giving
                it a home and more importantly a family.
            </p>

        </section>

        <section name="More about us">

            <p>
                <strong>
                    <a href="mailto:vmassol@apache.org">Vincent Massol</a>
                    -- Committer
                </strong>
                (written in 2002)
            </p>

            <p>
                I started designing internet applications in 1998, when I joined
                <a href="http://www.octo.com/">OCTO Technology</a>, an
                Information System Architecture Consulting company, providing
                expert IT Solutions and Application Architects in the field of new
                technologies (Application Servers, EAI, Internet Relationship
                Management). Very soon,
                when working on customer projects, I introduced the concept of unit
                testing (using JUnit) as a good way
                of writing reliable code. Although it worked very well for unit
                testing "standard" java classes, it was much more difficult for
                classes that used container objects. Thus, I began developing a small
                generic framework to help unit test servlets. I improved the
                framework as I moved on, from customer to customer.
            </p>

            <p>
                Until it was time to open source it! There were several drivers for that
                decision. As I spread the word about this framework within Octo,
                several octomen (and octowomen!) began using it and making
                modifications, and we
                ended up with several versions of it, making it difficult to
                synchronize them (although it was good for the evolutionary and
                darwinian side of it :) ). Another good reason was that I wanted to
                have feedback from the open source community and wanted to get help
                to improve it. Also, it was good to be able to provide to our
                customers a framework that would continue to evolve and be maintained
                even after we left the project. The last reason, maybe the strongest,
                is that I have always been fond of
                the open source concept and as Octo is providing consulting services,
                it did not clash with our business model !
            </p>
            <p>
                Thus, I moved the project to SourceForge and called it J2EEUnit. It
                did well and more and more persons were downloading, participating
                and using it.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now, most Applications Servers, EAI solutions or IRM ones are
                providing an infrastructure on which to build applications. But once
                you've bought the server, you're far from being finished ... There is
                the business logic code to write but there is also a lot of "glue" to
                implement. These are technical frameworks like a Controller of the
                MVC model, a logging framework, an XML-Java mapping one,
                application configuration, localization, templating, ... And usually
                these frameworks are not provided in the software package you buy.
                And even if they are (logging for example), they are not best of
                breed ones. For these frameworks, I have always been using open
                source solutions so far (Struts, Log4j, Ant, ...). Thus, I was
                lurking on Jakarta mailing-lists when I heard about a new project
                starting, called "Commons" which was to be a place where common
                components useful for several Jakarta projects would be found. I
                thought the idea of having a server-side java unit testing framework
                for Jakarta project (which are server side projects) was a good idea.
                I proposed to donate J2EEUnit to the Apache Software Foundation ...
                and I was lucky enough it was accepted ! :-)
            </p>
            <p>
                However, the J2EEUnit name was infringing on the Sun trademark on
                J2EE so we had to change the name. It was changed to Cactus (see the
                <a href="../cactusname.html">Why the name?</a>
                page for why this
                name). I found that in the move from SourceForge to Jakarta, I had
                found a new home for Cactus but, more importantly, I had found a
                family ! The sense of Community is very strong on Jakarta. You can
                feel right away the atmosphere and see it is different from other
                places.
            </p>
            <p>
                Then, thanks to Cactus growing community, our efforts were rewarded
                and Cactus was accepted as a Jakarta top level project, alongside
                the renowned Tomcat, Ant, Struts, ... waowww !
            </p>
            <p>
                We are now busy improving Cactus and looking for help. The first step
                was to get Cactus up and running and demonstrate it worked and is
                useful. This step has been achieved (I hope :) ). The second step is
                now to
                build a community around Cactus and find persons who are willing
                to actively participate in the future of it. Unit testing has
                still not reached the mainstream of development practices but is in
                the process of doing so with increasing interest in lightweight
                (also called "Agile") methodologies like Extreme Programming (XP).
                On the other hand, java server side programming is becoming stronger
                every day. This is to say that there is a bright future ahead for
                Cactus and there is still everything to invent.
            </p>
            <p>
                Although the project started as a one-man project, my goal has always
                been to relinquish as much as possible my hold on Cactus and make it
                a community-wide project. This is a work in progess and I am proud
                to say that I am no longer the only committer on the project and
                several persons have jumped aboard and are already helping shape
                Cactus future. Come and help us ! :)
            </p>
            <p>
                More info on my current open source involvements can be found
                <a href="http://blogs.codehaus.org/people/vmassol/">here</a>.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>
                    <a href="mailto:ndlesiecki@apache.org">Nicholas Lesiecki</a>
                    -- Committer
                </strong>
            </p>
            <p>
                I became involved in Cactus while co-authoring
                <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/047120708X/">Java Tools for Extreme
                    Programming</a>. (See
                our
                <a href="../resources/index.html#xp_book">resources</a>
                section for details.) While researching the framework I found myself
                making some suggestions on the project's mailing list. One thing led
                to another, and now I am graced with commiter status.
            </p>
            <p>
                I currently work as a Technical Team Lead at
                <a href="http://www.eblox.com/">eBlox, Inc</a>, a consulting and
                ecommerce application development shop. Right now I lead development of
                the company's flagship online catalog system,
                <a href="http://eblox.com/storeblox.php">storeBlox</a>. As such,
                I'm always working on new ways to test J2EE components, and so my
                involvement with Cactus is natural.
            </p>
            <p>
                I'm excited about Cactus 2.0, which we hope will usher in the next
                phase in in-container testing by providing a more abstract framework for
                interacting with a wider variety of containers (EJB, JMS, etc. ).
            </p>
            <p>
                <strong>
                    <a href="mailto:felipeal@apache.org">Felipe Leme</a>
                    -- Committer (written in October 2005)
                </strong>
            </p>
            <p>
                My first contact with unit testing happened in 2000, while working at Terraspring (a startup company
                later acquired by Sun), when my team was assigned to a manager with an XP background. At that time we
                were not using Cactus, only pure JUnit and some javascript unit testing tool.
                In 2002 I went back to Brazil, first working as consultant for an IT company in Sao Paulo and later (in
                2004) as a System Architect for a telecomunications in Campinas, where I had my first contact with
                Cactus. As the company already used Cactus in the development process and was migrating the building
                process to Maven, I got more involved with these two projects, fixing a bug here and suggesting an
                improvement there. After a few months of colaboration, I was nominated a committer for the Maven Plugins
                and later for Cactus - in both cases the nomination was proposed by Vincent.
            </p>
            <p>
                My main contributions were on the Maven integration, although I have done some stuff in the Ant
                integration as well. I wish I could do more, but unfortunately I am lacking the time to do so...
            </p>
            <p>
                <strong>
                    <a href="mailto:ptahchiev@apache.org">Petar Tahchiev</a>
                    -- Committer (written in January 2008)
                </strong>
            </p>
            <p>
                I started working with Cactus when trying to apply for the Google summer of code programme in 2007.
                Felipe Leme was my mentor but the project that we proposed was not accepted by the ASF. So I started
                to contribute on my own, out of the programme. I set up a repository in SourceForge and managed for
                a little more than 10 months to migrate the build system to Maven2. I also wanted to write a Maven2
                plugin for Cactus, but this one is still in my TODO list. At that time I finished the Cactus-Cargo
                integration, also closed a lot of bugs in the Jira improved the documentation, and made the new website.
            </p>
            <p>
                I am now starting of thinking for the next release, and after that I want to start developing the
                next-generation Cactus - Cactus2.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
