<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feature
      id="org.apache.cactus.eclipse.feature"
      label="org.apache.cactus.eclipse.feature"
      version="1.5.0"
      provider-name="Apache Software Foundation"
      image="logocactus.gif">

   <description>
      This feature includes the runner plug-in for Cactus and the webapp plug-in.
   </description>

   <license>
      /*
* ====================================================================
*
* The Apache Software License, Version 1.1
*
* Copyright (c) 2001-2003 The Apache Software Foundation.  All
rights
* reserved.
*
* Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
without
* modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
* are met:
*
* 1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
*    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
*
* 2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
copyright
*    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer
in
*    the documentation and/or other materials provided with the
*    distribution.
*
* 3. The end-user documentation included with the redistribution,
if
*    any, must include the following acknowlegement:
*       &quot;This product includes software developed by the
*        Apache Software Foundation (http://www.apache.org/).&quot;
*    Alternately, this acknowlegement may appear in the software
itself,
*    if and wherever such third-party acknowlegements normally
appear.
*
* 4. The names &quot;The Jakarta Project&quot;, &quot;Cactus&quot; and &quot;Apache Software
*    Foundation&quot; must not be used to endorse or promote products
*    derived from this software without prior written permission.
For
*    written permission, please contact apache@apache.org.
*
* 5. Products derived from this software may not be called &quot;Apache&quot;
*    nor may &quot;Apache&quot; appear in their names without prior written
*    permission of the Apache Group.
*
* THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED ``AS IS&apos;&apos; AND ANY EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED
* WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES
* OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
* DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE APACHE SOFTWARE FOUNDATION
OR
* ITS CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
* SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT
NOT
* LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS
OF
* USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED
AND
* ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
* OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY
WAY OUT
* OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY
OF
* SUCH DAMAGE.
* ====================================================================
*
* This software consists of voluntary contributions made by many
* individuals on behalf of the Apache Software Foundation.  For
more
* information on the Apache Software Foundation, please see
* &lt;http://www.apache.org/&gt;.
*
*/
   </license>

   <requires>
      <import plugin="org.apache.ant"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ant.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.boot"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.resources"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.runtime"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.debug.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.debug.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.debug"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.junit"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.launching"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.swt"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui"/>
   </requires>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.cactus.eclipse.runner"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="1.5.0"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.cactus.eclipse.webapp"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="1.5.0"/>

</feature>
